Guide to the Olivia Mattis Collection ARS.0107
Archive of Recorded Sound
Olivia Mattis Collection
1988-1990
ARS.0107
Mattis, Olivia
1 box: 17 10.5" open reel tapes
Archive of Recorded Sound
Interviews with avant-garde composers by musicologist Olivia Mattis.
Access
Open for research; material must be requested at least two business days in advance of intended use. Contact the Archive for assistance.
Scope and Contents
Interviews with avant-garde composers by musicologist Olivia Mattis, conducted while Mattis was a doctoral student at Stanford University studying Edgard Varèse. Thus, many of the subjects are family and associates of Varèse (many of whom are from the art world rather than music), and his name tends to come up in many of the interviews. Mattis was also the first person to interview Léon Thérémin after he emerged from over fifty years of Soviet seclusion in 1989. While the transcript for this interview has been published, less commonly found is the recording from the same tape of a theremin demonstration played by his daughter Natalia. The number of notable composers represented in the collection is impressive: Cage, Xenakis, Babbitt, Leuning, Schaeffer, Ussachevsky… Captured at the twilight of the twentieth century, there would be few further opportunities to hear the recollections of these brilliant creators. The collection also contains a rare interview with rock musician Frank Zappa, a known Varèse acolyte. Musicians, conductors, and artists are also among the interviewed. Sessions were in English and other languages (French, Russian) with an interpreter, and took place for the most part in Paris and New York City. These first generation copies (most of which have never been played) were dubbed from her original audiocassettes between 1989 and 1990, while Mattis was briefly employed at the Archive of Recorded Sound. Copies also appear to have been deposited at Yale University.
Source
The Olivia Mattis Collection was donated to the Stanford Archive of Recorded Sound by Olivia Mattis in 1990.
Arrangement
Reels have been numbered 1-17. Many interviews are contained on more than one reel. Approximate duration has been noted when evident.
Avant-garde (Music); Interviews
- Abravanel, Maurice, 1988-02-29 (Audio 1, Reel 15)
  Scope and Contents note
  Salt Lake City, Utah [ca. 90 min.].
  Abravanel, Maurice, 1903-1993
- Alcopley, L., 1988-07-29 (Audio 1, Reel 16)
  In his studio, Central Park West, New York City.
  Copley, Alfred L.
- Arel, Bülent, 1988-07-13 (Audio 1, Reel 14)
  With Daria Semegen and Vladimir Ussachevsky. Stonybrook, New York.
  Arel, Bülent, 1919-1990
- Arman, 1989-01-01 (Audio 1, Reel 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Armand Pierre Fernandez. Vence, France [ca. 60 min.].
  Arman, 1928-2005
- Babbitt, Milton, 1990-07-02 (Audio 1, Reel 4)
  In his studio at Julliard, New York City. 3-6:15 PM.
  Babbitt, Milton, 1916-2011
- Brown, Earle, 1990-03-30 (Audio 1, Reel 10)
  Venice, California [ca. 90 min.].
  Brown, Earle, 1926-2002
- Cage, John, 1988-07-28 (Audio 1, Reel 14)
  At his apartment on West 18th Street, New York City [ca. 60 min.].
  Cage, John
- Cavallo, Diana, 1988-07-30 (Audio 1, Reel 6)
  In her apartment on Broadway, New York City.
  Cavallo, Diana, 1931-
- Charlton, Maryette, 1988-07-18 (Audio 1, Reel 7, Reel 6)
  Charlton, Maryette
- Corner, Philip, 1989-12-27 (Audio 1, Reel 2)
  Corner, Philip
- Creuze, Raymond, 1989-09-05 (Audio 1, Reel 1)
  In his art gallery, 12 rue Beaujon, Paris [ca. 53 min.].
  Creuze, Raymond
- Dlugoszewski, Lucia, 1989-12-29 (Audio 1, Reel 2)
  Erick Hawkins Dance School, New York City. 4:30-5:15 PM [ca. 45 min.].
  Dlugoszewski, Lucia, 1931-2000
- Emmett, Dorothy Morang, 1989-11-08 (Audio 1, Reel 10)
  At her home in Sante Fe, New Mexico [ca. 40 min.].
  Emmett, Dorothy Morang
- Guttman, Newman, 1988-07-06 (Audio 1, Reel 12)
  At his home in Evanston, Illinois.
  Guttman, Newman
- Heller, Red, 1989-12-29 (Audio 1, Reel 2)
  With Ernest Heller (her husband) and Charles Schwartz, founder of Composer's Showcase. At the home of Red And Ernest (Dick) Heller in New York City. 1:30-2:30 PM.
  Heller, Red, 1898-2003
- Jolas, Betsy, 1989-02-09 (Audio 1, Reel 3)
  At her apartment on rue Bonaparte, Paris. 6:20-7:30 PM [ca. 70 min.].
  Jolas, Betsy
- Jolivet, Hilda, 1989-08-27 (Audio 1, Reel 8)
  at her home on rue de Varenne, Paris. 2:30 PM [ca. 75 min.].
  Jolivet, Hilda
- Kiesler, Lillian, 1988-07-18 (Audio 1, Reel 12)
  At her apartment in New York City [ca. 45 min.].
  Kiesler, Lillian
- Leeuw, Ton de, 1989 (Audio 1, Reel 8)
  at his home on rue de la Convention, Paris. May 12 and September 5, 1989 [ca. 80 min.].
  Leeuw, Ton de, 1926-1996
- Luening, Otto, 1988-07-12 (Audio 1, Reel 15)
  New York City.
  Luening, Otto, 1900-1996
- McMillan, Ann, 1988-11 (Audio 1, Reel 11)
  New York City, November 9 and 13, 1988. At her apartment, on the street, at Cooper Union while waiting for a John Cage concert to begin, and then at her apartment again.
  McMillan, Ann
- Mimaroğlu, Ilhan, 1988-07-12 (Audio 1, Reel 13)
  At Finnadar/Atlantic Records, New York City [ca 65 min.].
  Mimaroğlu, Ilhan K. (Ilhan Kemaleddin), 1926-
- Pierce, John, 1988-01 (Audio 1, Reel 12)
  [ca. 50 min.].
  Pierce, John R. (John Robinson), 1910-2002
- Pierce, John; Pierce, Brenda; Mathews, Max; Mathews, Marjorie, 1988-08-18 (Audio 1, Reel 13)
  At the Pierce residence.
  Mathews, Max V.; Pierce, John R. (John Robinson), 1910-2002
- Rifkin, Joshua, 1989-10-11 (Audio 1, Reel 1)
  Stanford office [ca. 45 min.].
  Rifkin, Joshua
- Risset, Jean-Claude, 1988-12-26 (Audio 1, Reel 3)
  Olivia's apartment, Paris [ca. 90 min.].
  Risset, Jean-Claude
- Rower, Howard, 1988-07-23 (Audio 1, Reel 5)
  Cafe Dante, New York City. 8:00 PM. Rower is Alexander Calder's son-in-law. [ca. 45 min.].
  Rower, Howard
- Schaeffer, Pierre, 1989-03-06 (Audio 1, Reel 2)
  In his apartment, rue Des Petits Champs, Paris. 5:00 PM [ca. 40 min.].
  Schaeffer, Pierre, 1910-1995
- Schic, Anna Stella, 1989-01-20 (Audio 1, Reel 3)
  With Michel Philippot. Paris, 5:30 PM. Schic (Mme. Philippot) speaks at the beginning about the relations between Varèse and Villa-Lobos, her master.
  Philippot, Michel, Michel, 1925-1996; Schic, Anna Stella
- Schneemann, Carolee, 1988-07-14 (Audio 1, Reel 5)
  [ca. 60 min.].
  Schneemann, Carolee, 1939-
- Slonimsky, Nicolas, 1988-04 (Audio 1, Reel 17)
  At his home in Los Angeles, California, April 2-3, 1988.
  Slonimsky, Nicolas, 1894-1995
- Tenney, James, 1990-04-28 (Audio 1, Reel 9)
  At the home of Max and Marjorie Mathews in Palo Alto, California, with Max and Marjorie Mathews, John and Brenda Pierce, and Todd and Marina Winkler. 10:30 -12:00PM [ca. 90 min.].
  Tenney, James
- Thérémin, Léon (Lev), 1989-06 (Audio 1, Reel 9)
  June 16 and 18, 1989: Portion of interview takes place on airplane during take off. June 17, 1989: demonstration of Thereminvox by Thérémin's daughter Natalia Thérémin, Bourges, France at the 19th International Experimental Music Festival.
  Thérémin, Léon, 1896-1993
- Ussachevsky, Vladimir, 1988-02-28 (Audio 1, Reel 17, Reel 16)
  Salt Lake City, Utah.
  Ussachevsky, Vladimir, 1911-1990
- Varèse, Claude, 1988-12 (Audio 1, Reel 7, Reel 8)
  Claude is Edgard Varèse's daughter. December 29, 1988 at Cafe de Paris, Monte Carlo, with Claude's daughter Marilyn Mulder Vespier; December 31, 1988 in her apartment on boulevard d'Italie in Monte Carlo.
  Varèse, Edgard, 1883-1965
- Varèse, Louise, 1988-06 (Audio 1, Reel 6, Reel 5)
  Eugene, Oregon. June 1-3, 1988. Widow of Edgard Varèse, b. 1890. With Michael Norton (Louise's son), Loa Norton (Michael's wife), Sylvia Gillis (Michael and Loa's daughter), and David Calderwood (Sylvia's fiance).
  Varèse, Edgard, 1883-1965; Varèse, Louise
- Weinberg, Henry, 1988-08-01 (Audio 1, Reel 13)
  New York City [ca. 70 min.].
  Weinberg, Henry, 1931-
- Wigglesworth, Frank, 1989-09-23 (Audio 1, Reel 8)
  at his home on Downing Street, New York City [ca. 70 min.].
  Wigglesworth, Frank, 1918-1996
- Wood, Beatrice, 1988-03-30 (Audio 1, Reel 17)
  Ojai, California.
  Wood, Beatrice
- Xenakis, Iannis, 1989 (Audio 1, Reel 7)
  At his studio on rue Victor Masse, Paris. May 22 and June 8, 1989.
  Xenakis, Iannis, 1922-2001
- Zappa, Frank, 1990-03-30 (Audio 1, Reel 10)
  At his home in Hollywood, California [ca. 60 min.].
  Zappa, Frank